William Cary Sanger and Ethel Sanger Papers
William Cary Sanger and Ethel Sanger Papers
1884-1929
Sanger, Wm. Cary (William Cary), 1853-1921.
3.25 linear ft.
Papers of the US Assistant Secretary of War (1901-1903) William Cary Sanger and those of his wife Ethel Sanger, mostly in the form of correspondence
2707529
Biographical History
William Cary Sanger (1853-1921) was an American military man and government official. He served as US Assistant Secretary of War from 1901-1903.
Sanger was born in Brooklyn, New York on May 21, 1853. He attended Brooklyn Polytechnic and graduated from Harvard in 1874 with a BA. He earned an LL.B. (undergraduate law degree) from Columbia University in 1878, and was awarded the honorary LL.D. degree from Hamilton College in 1902. Sanger served two years in the New York State Assembly (1895-1897)and as United States Assistant Secretary of War from 1901 to 1903. He was president of the American delegation to the Geneva Convention of 1906, and from 1911 to 1913 he ws a member of the New York State Hospital Commission.
Sanger and his wife Ethel (Mary Ethel Cleveland Dodge, 1869-1952) had no children.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The William Cary Sanger and Ethel Sanger Papers consist of correspondence of William, correspondence of his wife Ethel, and subject files. The bulk of the correspondence is from 1900 to 1922.
Correspondence of William Sanger consists of letters sent to and from William, mostly regarding his tenure as the Assistant Secretary of War (1901-1903). Much of the correspondence is on various government letterheads.
Correspondence of Ethel Sanger consists mostly of incoming personal correspondence, with a few items of outgoing correspondence from her. Dates of her correspondence extend to after her husband's death.
Subject files consist of two scrapbooks, which appear to have been created in memoriam for Sanger, presumably by his wife after his death in 1921, as well as poetry, material on the Geneva Convention Conference of 1906, material on a Red Cross Conference in 1907, and correspondence and notes regarding the Sanger family.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is divided into William's and Ethel's, and then arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Subject files are alphabetical by topic.
Related Material
The New York State Library has a substantial collection of Sanger's papers.
Subject and Genre Headings
Military history; Politics, government and public administration; Hughes, Charles Evans, 1862-1948.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919.; Root, Elihu, 1845-1937.; Sanger, Ethel.; Sanger, Wm. Cary (William Cary), 1853-1921.; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930.; Geneva Convention (1906 July 6); International Conference of the Red Cross.; United States -- War Department.; Government executives -- United States.; Politicians -- New York State.; Politicians -- United States.; New York (State); Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Scrapbooks.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift, 1968.
Inventory
- Correspondence, William Sanger
  - Abrams, Charles W., 1919 (Box 1)
  - Adler, Alvey A., 1901-1902 (Box 1)
  - Ailes, Milton E., 1901 (Box 1)
  - Ainsworth, D.E., 1894; 1901 (Box 1)
  - Appleton, Francis R., 1901; 1905-1906,; 1917-1919 (Box 1)
  - Astor, John Jacob, 1902 (Box 1)
  - A, misc, 1901; 1905-1906,; 1918 (Box 1)
  - Babbott, Frank L., 1901; 1908 (Box 1)
  - Bacon, Robert, 1906 (Box 1)
  - Bailey, E. Prentiss, 1908-1909; 1911 (Box 1)
  - Bailey, L.H., 1905; 1911 (Box 1)
  - Baker, Newton D., 1916-1918 (Box 1)
  - Balfour, Eustace, 1900 (Box 1)
  - Belmont, August, 1900; 1905,; 1908,; 1913 (Box 1)
  - Benson, G.J., 1901 (Box 1)
  - Blair, Elmer, 1898; 1901 (Box 1)
  - Boardman, Marie, 1905 (Box 1)
  - Breckinridge, J.C., 1901 (Box 1)
  - Bryce, James, 1908-1909; 1911 (Box 1)
  - Butler, Nicholas, 1901; 1905,; 1908-1909 (Box 1)
  - B, misc, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Calder, J.F., 1901 (Box 1)
  - Carey, Sam, 1901 (Box 1)
  - Carter, William, 1904 (Box 1)
  - Choate, Joseph H., 1901; 1908,; 1910 (Box 1)
  - Clauson, John E., 1900 (Box 1)
  - Colville, William, undated (Box 1)
  - Cortelyou, G.B., 1901; 1903 (Box 1)
  - Crawshaw, William H., 1909 (Box 1)
  - C, misc, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Darbin, Winfield, 1903 (Box 1)
  - Dana, Richard H., 1902; 1905,; 1921,; 1925 (Box 1)
  - Darling, C.W., 1894; 1901 (Box 1)
  - Davis, Colwell Boothe, 1912 (Box 1)
  - [Lord] Denbigh, 1907; 1920 (Box 1)
  - Dick, Charles, 1902-1905 (Box 1)
  - Dix, John A., 1911 (Box 1)
  - Dodge, William E., 1902-1903 (Box 1)
  - Dunham, George E., 1901; 1905 (Box 1)
  - Dyer, Louis, 1902; 1904,; 1907 (Box 1)
  - D, misc (Box 1)
  - E, misc, 1902-1907; 1909,; 1919 (Box 1)
  - F, misc, 1887; 1901-1907,; 1914,; 1920-1922 (Box 1)
  - G, misc, 1884; 1901-1909,; 1912,; 1916 (Box 2)
  - Hughes, Charles E., 1906-1908; 1916 (Box 2)
  - H, misc, 1888; 1900-1907,; 1916-1921; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - I, misc, 1901 (Box 2)
  - J, misc, 1895; 1900-1908,; 1911 (Box 2)
  - K, misc, 1894; 1901-1909,; 1918 (Box 2)
  - L, misc, 1891; 1894,; 1901-1903,; 1906-1907,; 1916-1918,; 1921 (Box 2)
  - M, misc, 1894; 1897,; 1901-1911,; 1917,; 1920-1921 (Box 2)
  - N, misc, 1900; 1905 (Box 2)
  - O, misc, 1891; 1896,; 1900-1908,; 1916-1917,; 1919 (Box 2)
  - P, misc, 1894; 1900-1910,; 1915-1917,; 1929 (Box 2)
  - Roosevelt, Theodore, 1903; 1905 (Box 2)
  - Root, Elihu, 1896; 1900-1911,; 1918 (Box 2)
  - R, misc, 1894; 1901-1903,; 1909-1912,; 1917-1918,; 1920 (Box 2)
  - S, misc, 1887-1888; 1894-1898,; 1900-1912,; 1916,; 1920-1921; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Taft, William H., 1905; 1908,; 1912,; 1916-1917, (Box 3)
  - T, misc, 1901-1912; 1917-1918,; 1920 (Box 3)
  - U, misc, 1901 (Box 3)
  - V, misc, 1901-1908; 1916 (Box 3)
  - W, misc, 1894; 1898,; 1900-1909,; 1916-1921; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - X-Y, misc, 1901-1902; 1918 (Box 3)
  - First name only, 1901; 1916,; 1921 (Box 3)
  - Illegible, 1888; 1901-1903,; 1907-1911,; 1914-1921 (Box 3)
- Correspondence, Ethel Sanger
  - A-R, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - S-V (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, unidentified or illegible (Box 4)
- Subject files
  - Elihu Root, 1902-1903 (Box 4)
  - Geneva Convention Conference, 1906 (Box 4)
  - Poetry, undated; typescript and handwritten, author unknown (Box 4)
  - Red Cross Conference, 1907 (Box 4)
  - Sanger family, 1901; 1910,; 1917,; 1919; correspondence, notes (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook, in memoriam of William Cary Sanger (Oversize 1)
  - Scrapbook, in memoriam of William Cary Sanger (Oversize 2)
  - Miscellaneous about Sanger, 1894; 1908,; 1914,; 1917,; 1920,; 1922; memorabilia, membership cards, notes/lettes about, etc. (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1888; 1900,; 1903,; 1916,; 1918,; 1921 (Box 4)